In the last video, we set up and ran a coupled muscle and fat simulation.
지난 영상에서는 근육과 지방을 결합한 시뮬레이션을 설정하고 실행했습니다.
You can see we have some interesting bicep bulge reflected on the fat layer.
지방 레이어에서 이두근이 불룩해지는 흥미로운 형태가 잘 반영된 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
Now let's go ahead and start generating a geometry cache and use that to train a multiformer.
이제 지오메트리 캐시를 생성하고, 그것을 사용해 ML 디포머를 학습해 보겠습니다.
So first thing we're going to do is go ahead and create a generate surface binding node.
먼저 ‘Generate Surface Binding’ 노드를 만들어 줍니다.
This will generate bindings from the skin layer to the fat layer.
이 노드는 피부 레이어에서 지방 레이어로의 바인딩을 생성합니다.
And over here, let's set our skeletal mesh to be the skin.
여기에서 Skeletal Mesh는 피부(스킨)로 설정하겠습니다.
Choose the blunt one.
블렌드 버전을 선택하세요.
And search radius 1.0.
Search Radius는 1.0으로 둡니다.
Now it starts to evaluate.
이제 계산이 시작됩니다.
Good. We just have the results.
좋습니다. 결과가 나왔네요.
And you can see the skin.
여기 보이는 것이 피부입니다.
What you've seen is the skin here.
여기서 보신 것이 바로 이 스킨입니다.
Inside the spring constraints for a second.
잠시 스프링 제약(Spring Constraints)으로 들어가 보겠습니다.
It's color coded.
색상으로 표시되어 있습니다.
And you can check out the meaning of the color here.
색상의 의미는 여기에서 확인할 수 있습니다.
Basically, if you don't see red, it's good.
기본적으로 빨간색이 보이지 않으면 잘된 것입니다.
Blue and green is there either inside the tetrahedral mesh or on the surface of the tetrahedral mesh.
파란색과 초록색은 사면체 메시에 포함되어 있거나 그 표면에 있다는 뜻입니다.
So this is good.
그래서 이 상태는 괜찮습니다.
And let's save that information.
이 정보를 저장하겠습니다.
Plug that in.
저것을 여기에 연결하세요.
And now we have the information saved in the flesh asset.
이제 해당 정보가 Flesh 에셋 안에 저장되었습니다.
At this point, we can create a geometry cache so that we can save things in there.
이 시점에서 지오메트리 캐시를 만들어 그 안에 결과를 저장할 수 있습니다.
Click new geometry cache.
새 지오메트리 캐시를 클릭합니다.
And let's call this the geometry cache.
이 이름을 ‘GeometryCache’로 하겠습니다.
Looks good.
괜찮아 보입니다.
And embedded skeletal mesh.
Embedded Skeletal Mesh 옵션을 켭니다.
Make sure we're giving it exactly the same thing as here.
여기서도 위와 정확히 같은 것을 지정해야 합니다.
The skeletal mesh.
Skeletal Mesh 말이죠.
It's the blend one.
블렌드 버전입니다.
Choose that.
그걸 선택하세요.
And now we can click generate geometry cache.
이제 ‘Generate Geometry Cache’를 누를 수 있습니다.
Let's do that.
진행해 보겠습니다.
Now it's evaluating.
현재 계산 중입니다.
It's interpolating from the chaos cache or the tetrahedral mesh simulation.
Chaos 캐시(또는 사면체 메쉬) 시뮬레이션에서 보간하고 있습니다.
You can see now we have the geometry cache here.
이제 여기 지오메트리 캐시가 생성된 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
Let's double click that and view the geometry cache.
더블 클릭해서 지오메트리 캐시를 열어 보겠습니다.
You can see this is actually the skin.
보시다시피 이건 실제로 피부(스킨)입니다.
It's not the fat layer anymore.
더 이상 지방 레이어가 아닙니다.
It's the skin.
스킨입니다.
But it's doing the bicep curl animation.
하지만 이두 컬(bicep curl) 애니메이션을 수행하고 있죠.
This is interpolated from the simulation.
이것은 시뮬레이션으로부터 보간된 결과입니다.
And that's good.
좋습니다.
Let's go ahead and use this geometry cache to train ML deformer.
이 지오메트리 캐시를 사용해서 ML 디포머를 학습해 보겠습니다.
And to do that, let's go ahead and create a new ML deformer asset.
그러려면 새 ML Deformer 에셋을 만들겠습니다.
And let's call this one the email ML deformer.
이름은 ‘Emil_ML_Deformer’로 하죠.
Double click that.
더블 클릭합니다.
And over here, you can see this is the empty ML deformer.
여기 비어 있는 ML 디포머 에셋이 보입니다.
And the skeletal mesh to escape the skin.
Skeletal Mesh는 스킨으로 설정합니다.
Let's load the animation.
애니메이션을 로드합시다.
Remember, we use the bicep curl animation mixture.
기억하세요, 우리는 BicepCurl 애니메이션 시퀀스를 사용했습니다.
You have to make sure the animation match the simulation that you ran.
학습에 사용하는 애니메이션은 시뮬레이션에 사용한 것과 반드시 일치해야 합니다.
So remember, we ran the simulation on bicep curl animation.
우리는 이두 컬 애니메이션으로 시뮬레이션을 돌렸습니다.
Let's give it the geometry cache.
이제 지오메트리 캐시를 지정합니다.
And it's got 90 frames of data.
프레임은 90개가 들어 있습니다.
Right?
맞죠?
Now we can see that it says the training process needs inputs.
이제 ‘학습(Training)’에는 입력이 필요하다는 메시지가 보일 겁니다.
Let's go ahead and provide some network inputs.
네트워크 입력을 추가하겠습니다.
Which will be the joints that controls the skeletal mesh.
스켈레탈 메쉬를 제어하는 조인트(본)들이 입력이 됩니다.
At this point, let's add all enemy bones.
이 시점에서 ‘모든 본 추가(Add All Bones)’를 하겠습니다.
So this will add all 54 joints that controls the skeletal mesh.
그러면 스켈레탈 메쉬를 제어하는 54개의 조인트가 모두 추가됩니다.
And you can later on prune the list to only keep the major joints.
나중에 목록을 가지치기(prune)해서 주요 조인트만 남길 수 있습니다.
This allows you to save memory or save the number of parameters used in a network.
이렇게 하면 메모리를 절약하고 네트워크의 파라미터 수도 줄일 수 있습니다.
Once we have that set up, let's use the default parameter to set the number of iterations.
설정이 끝났으니 반복 횟수는 기본값으로 두겠습니다.
Let's do some quick training.
빠르게 한 번 학습을 돌려 보죠.
Just as a proof of concept that we can do this.
가능하다는 것을 보여 주는 수준의 간단한 예시입니다.
After that, let's click train model.
그럼 ‘Train Model(모델 학습)’을 클릭합니다.
So you can see that loss is already decreasing.
보시다시피 손실 값(loss)이 이미 감소하고 있습니다.
You can use more iterations to decrease the loss.
반복 횟수를 더 늘리면 손실을 더 줄일 수 있습니다.
And of course, we're using example training data.
물론, 지금은 예제용 학습 데이터를 쓰고 있습니다.
This is not usually the number of frames that you want.
보통 원하는 프레임 수에 비해 적습니다.
It's only 90 frames.
여기는 90프레임뿐입니다.
For the horse example, we use 5,000 frames.
말(Kelpie) 예시에서는 약 5,000프레임을 사용했습니다.
We use the strength training data.
그건 비교를 위한 더 큰 규모의 학습 데이터였죠.
Just as a comparison.
단지 비교용 참고 자료라고 보시면 됩니다.
And now, I'm going to go ahead and go to testing mode.
이제 테스트 모드로 넘어가겠습니다.
You can just validate the training result by setting the animation, test animation, to be exactly the same as the training data.
검증은 테스트용 애니메이션을 학습에 사용한 것과 완전히 동일하게 설정해서 진행할 수 있습니다.
Just to see if it fits.
맞게 맞춰지는지만 확인해 보는 거죠.
Alright, we can also bring in the ground truth.
이제 ‘정답(ground truth)’도 불러올 수 있습니다.
Let's bring in the heat map.
히트맵을 켜 보겠습니다.
Let's see where the deltas are being applied.
델타가 어디에 적용되는지 확인해 보죠.
See, it's applying a lot of delta on devices.
보시다시피 이두근 부위에 큰 델타가 많이 적용되고 있습니다.
Of course, like I said, you can increase the number of training iterations to prove the accuracy of the network.
말씀드렸듯이 반복 횟수를 늘리면 네트워크 정확도를 더 높일 수 있습니다.
But here, we're just proving the concept.
여기서는 개념 증명(proof of concept)만 보여 드렸습니다.